Finding Aid for Michigan Ecumenical Forum records, 1916-2002
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Organizational Activities and Units
  - Church in Society
    - Peace Education Program (PEP)
      - National and local priorities in spending
        - Committee 1969 (Box 19)
        - Workshop 1969 (Box 19)
      - Office memos 1968-1969 (Box 19)
      - Staff 1968-1969 (Box 19)
    - Planning documents
      - "Directions for the Division of Church and Society" undated (Box 19)
        (facilitate cooperation between denominations and churches)
      - "A Strategy Proposal: Division of Church and Society" 1967 (Box 19)
        (focus work on Vietnam and urban issues)
    - Racism and hate groups: correspondence, conference materials, and clippings 1994-1999 (Box 19)
      (includes photographs and materials related to Michigan church burnings)
    - Social Relations Committee 1961-1964 (Box 20)
    - State Citizenship Conference 1953 (Box 20)
    - Surrogate parenting 1983 (Box 20)
    - Urban issues 1978-1979, 1984 (Box 20)
    - Williams International Peace Demonstration (Walled Lake): protests and arrests 1983-1984 (Box 20)
  - Education
    The Education subseries contains records of the Division of Christian Education and various committees as well as materials related to continuing education for clergy and the School for Ministry. The Division's materials focus largely on Sunday school and youth camps but also reflect concerns over the intersection of religion and public education. The continuing education materials detail consultations and initiatives aimed at providing clergy with ongoing ecumenical education. The School for Ministry materials detail the MCC/MEF's collaboration with this non-accredited ecumenical education institution.
    - Division of Christian Education
      - General meeting minutes, reports, and related materials 1946-1968, 9 folders (Box 20)
      - Church School Study
        - General 1962-1966, 3 folders (Box 20)
        - Correspondence 1964-1967 (Box 20)
        - Finances 1964-1965 (Box 20)
        - "A Study of Christian Education Program and Personnel in Michigan Churches" by R. K. Ordway 1965 (Box 20)
      - Committees
        - Adult Education and Work 1956-1963 (Box 20)
        - Camp 1958-1972, 7 folders (Box 20)
          (includes materials related to youth camp conferences and camp leaders' training)
        - Campus Strategy 1956-1963 (Box 20)
        - Children's Work 1960-1965 (Box 20)
        - Laboratory Training 1967-1972, 3 folders (Box 20)
        - Youth Work Committee 1958-1966 (Box 21)
      - Purpose and goals of the Division 1940s (Box 21)
      - Workshops, consultations, and conferences
        - Ecumenical education 1966-1967 (Box 21)
        - Educational planning 1968 (Box 21)
        - Federal aid and education 1965 (Box 21)
        - Religion and public education 1967 (Box 21)
        - Sex education 1966-1967 (Box 21)
    - Continuing Education for Clergy
      (originally an initiative of the Division of Christian Education)
      - Committee 1989-1993 (Box 21)
      - Consultations
        - 1966-1967 (Box 21)
        - 1988 (Box 21)
      - Professional Continuing Ecumenical Education (PROCEED) 1972-1973, 5 folders (Box 21)
    - School for Ministry
      - Board meetings: minutes, correspondence, and reports 1982-1989, 5 folders (Box 21)
      - Executive Committee (Southeast Michigan) 1981 (Box 21)
      - Financial reports 1983-1985 (Box 21)
      - Homecoming 1987 (Box 21)
      - Newsletters and mailings 1985-1987 (Box 21)
      - Personnel 1985-1986 (Box 21)
      - Policy Board 1982 (Box 21)
        (includes the School for Ministry's bylaws)
      - Slides undated (Box 21)
      - Miscellaneous 1985-1986 (Box 21)
  - Interchurch Unity and Cooperation
    The Interchurch Unity and Cooperation subseries consists of records from the Division of Christian Unity as well as materials related to the development of local church councils and Regional Ecumenical Forum (with a heavy emphasis on the Upper Peninsula). Content reflects interaction with other denominations and non-Christian faiths and conferences and reports dealing with interchurch collaboration.
    - Christian Unity and Interreligious Concerns Commission 2000-2001 (Box 22)
    - Division of Christian Unity
      - General 1965-1969, 2 folders (Box 22)
      - Faith and Order Study and Summit
        - Correspondence and minutes 1964-1967 (Box 22)
        - Seminar on Conciliar Development 1967 (Box 22)
        - Summit Conference 1967 (Box 22)
      - Conference on Protestant Needs and Resources 1955-1956 (Box 22)
      - Interfaith Circles Jewish-Christian Dialogue 1989 (Box 22)
      - Michigan Workshop on Christian Unity 1983-1984 (Box 22)
      - Muslim, Christian, Jewish Leadership Forum 1994 (Box 22)
      - National Workshop on Christian Unity 1982 (Box 22)
      - Pastors' Conferences 1940-1969, 3 folders (Box 22)
      - "The Resource Connection": Shared Resource Consultation 1988 (Box 22)
    - Formula of Agreement between Evangelical Luthern Church in America, the Presbyterian Church, U.S.A., the Reformed Church in America, and the United Church of Christ 1998 (Box 22)
    - Regional Development of Ecumenical Forums
      - Area Councils of Churches 1950s-1970s (Box 22)
        (includes material from Bay County, Detroit, Grand Rapids, and Lansing)
      - Directory of Michigan Interchurch Agencies and related correspondence 1970 (Box 22)
        (includes list of Michigan Regional/Area Ecumenical Organizations, 1985)
      - Lansing Area Regional Ecumenical Forum 1982, 1987 (Box 22)
      - Local, Regional, and State Ecumenical Staff: meeting materials and correspondence 1968-1980 (Box 22)
      - Manual for Local Councils circa 1946 (Box 22)
        (includes suggestions for fund raising and reports on social education and action committees)
      - Northern Regional Ecumenical Forum 1986-1987 (Box 22)
      - Saginaw Regional Ecumenical Forum 1984-1986 (Box 22)
      - Upper Peninsula
        - Council of Churches 1966-1968 (Box 22)
        - Pastor's Conferences 1958-1971, 1985, 4 folders (Box 22)
          (also referred to as Clergy Conferences)
        - Peace Education Program 1970-1972 (Box 22)
        - Upper Great Lakes Regional Commission (UGLRC): progress report, economic development, and consultations 1967-1970, 4 folders (Box 22)
      - Various Regional Ecumenical Forums 1985 (Box 22)
    - Reports
      - "The Relationship of the State and Local Councils of Churches" undated (Box 22)
      - "Relations between the Michigan and National Councils of Churches" undated (Box 22)
    - Rituals and Sacraments
      - Baptism 1995-1998 (Box 22)
      - Eucharist 1998 (Box 22)
  - Missions and Outreach
    The Missions and Outreach subseries consists of meeting minutes, reports, and correspondence related to the MCC/MEF's ministry to various populations. Materials relate to the aging, Native Americans, migrant workers and rural communities as well as a radio and television campaign from the 1960s. Much of the material stems from the Division of Christian Mission.
    - Aging
      - Coalition on Ministry and Aging 1977-1980 (Box 23)
      - Interfaith Ministry with the Aging 1984-1987 (Box 23)
    - Deaf, Mission for the 1965-1969 (Box 23)
    - Leisure and Recreation Ministry: meeting materials and reports 1966-1971, 2 folders (Box 23)
    - Michigan Indians
      - General 1969-1973 (Box 23)
      - Community Action Program 1968 (Box 23)
      - Consultation 1967-1969, 2 folders (Box 23)
      - Indian Affairs 1967-1969 (Box 23)
      - Medical Screening Project 1968-1969 (Box 23)
    - Michigan Migrant Ministry
      - General 1957-1962 (Box 23)
      - Annual reports 1965-1969 (Box 23)
      - Area meetings 1965-1969 (Box 23)
      - Settling Migrants Report 1967 (Box 23)
      - Miscellaneous 1968-1969 (Box 23)
      - Michigan Farm Worker Ministry 1975-1987 (Box 23)
    - Radio-Television Committee
      - Correspondence 1965-1969 (Box 23)
      - Minutes 1964-1969 (Box 23)
      - "Possible Plan for Michigan Council Radio Program" 1951 (Box 23)
      - Project Choice 1967-1969 (Box 23)
    - Resource Packet: "Discovering God's Mission in Our Community" 1968 (Box 23)
    - Rural Ministry 1986-1994, 11 folders (Box 23)
      (includes material related to Farm Aid and Rural Social Science by Extension)
    - Town and Country Church, Committee on 1960s (Box 23)
  - General Issues, Initiatives, and Partnerships
    The General Issues, Initiatives, and Partnerships subseries contains meeting minutes, correspondence, and reports related to the MCC/MEF's participation in various coalitions and partnerships as well as initiatives unassociated with specific organizational divisions. The records document specific events as well as planning sessions and regular meetings. Significant materials include those related to the Michigan Church Leaders (an organization of denominational heads formed contemporaneously with the MEF), the Michigan Ecumenical Consultation on Christianity and Ecology (MECCE), and Michigan Interfaith Impact (also known as Michigan Impact and Michigan Agenda).
    - Association of Church Secretaries: meeting minutes, roster, and constitution 1965-1969 (Box 24)
    - Association for Faith-Based Development 1990s (Box 24)
    - Christian Science Committee on Publication for Michigan 1997 (Box 24)
      (collaboration regarding SB 446)
    - Coalition for the Free Exercise of Religion 1998 (Box 24)
    - Events
      - "Dialogue on the Common Good: Seeking a Sustainable Society" 1991-1992, 6 folders; contains two audio cassette recording of the 1992 proceedings (Box 24)
      - MCC Convocation 1981-1982 (Box 24)
      - Michigan Sesquicentennial 1987 (Box 24)
      - Michigan Stand for Children 1996 (Box 24)
      - Music Workshop with Michigan State University 1966 (Box 24)
      - Open House 1965 (Box 24)
      - Spring Conference for Clergy and Lay Leaders (in Bay City) 1989 (Box 24)
      - Vocation of the Laity 1988 (Box 24)
      - "Work and Justice at the Century's Turn: a Religion and Labor Dialogue" 1997 (Box 24)
      - Miscellaneous 1984-1997 (Box 24)
    - Family Farm Concerns Coalition 1976-1981 (Box 24)
    - Grant proposals and related materials 1995-2001 (Box 24)
    - Lansing Multicultural Education 1995 (Box 24)
    - Michigan Church Leaders
      - "Bitter Harvest" (welfare and General Assistance): press conference materials and clippings 1991, 2 folders (Box 24)
      - Directory 1995-1996 (Box 24)
      - Persian Gulf War: correspondence, press releases, clippings, etc. 1990-1991, 4 folders (Box 24)
      - Retreats
        - General planning materials 1982-1998, 4 folders (Box 24)
        - Agendas, correspondence, and additional materials 1991-2000, 17 folders (Box 25)
    - Michigan Council on Crime and Delinquency 1975-1976 (Box 25)
      (includes related materials from various MCC task forces and committees)
    - Michigan Ecumenical Church Secretaries Association 1990-1991 (Box 25)
    - Michigan Ecumenical Consultation on Christianity and Ecology (MECCE)
      - General: meeting materials, correspondence, and reports 1994-2001, 3 folders (Box 25)
      - Correspondence 1996-1997 (Box 25)
      - Mailing list 1994 (Box 25)
      - Resource bibliography 1993 (Box 25)
      - MECCE conference materials 1995-1996, 1998, 2000, 4 folders (Box 25)
    - Michigan Interfaith Disaster Response (MIDR): meeting minutes, correspondence, and related materials 1974-1989, 8 folders (Box 25)
    - Michigan Interfaith Hunger Action Coalition 1978-1981 (Box 25)
    - Michigan Interfaith Impact
      (previously known as Michigan Impact and Michigan Agenda)
      - Constitution and board members 1983-1993 (Box 26)
      - Newsletters 1977-1993, 2 folders (Box 26)
      - Program materials, meeting minutes, correspondence, etc. 1982-1998, 8 folders (Box 26)
      - Reorganization, law suit, and associated negotiations 1983-1985, 3 folders (Box 26)
    - Michigan Peace Network 1981-1982 (Box 26)
    - Michigan Theologians 1983-1987 (Box 26)
    - National Council of the Churches of Christ in the USA (NCCC) 2001 (Box 26)
    - Partners of the Alliance (Development Planning for Belize) 1966-1969, 2 folders (Box 26)
    - Working for Justice: conference materials, correspondence, and related documents 1995-1996, 8 folders (Box 27)
    - World Hunger Education/Action Together 1976-1978 (Box 27)
    - Miscellaneous Michigan Issues 1982-1985 (Box 27)
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Materials series contains photographs of various MCC/MEF officers, events, and activities as well as VHS video recordings of several church services.
  - Photographs: people and events, 1940s-1980s, 3 folders (Box 27)
    (includes material previously stored in a photo album)
  - Videotapes
    - Children's Church 1996 (Box 27)
    - "One Spirit, One Body, One Baptism" (Westminster Presbyterian Church) 1995 (Box 27)
Related Material
Additional materials related to the MCC/MEF are located with the Michigan Historical Commission in the Michigan State Archives in Lansing. An item list of these materials (which include meeting minutes, correspondence, and publications spanning 1886-1960) is available among the "Early Records and Predecessor Organizations" in Box 6 of the collection.